Register of the Leon Volkov Papers, 1948-1974
Hoover Institution Archives
Leon Volkov Papers,
1948-1974
77088
Volkov, Leon, 1914-1974
7 manuscript boxes 2.9 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Diaries, correspondence, speeches and writings, reports, clippings, press excerpts, and printed matter, relating to social and political conditions in the Soviet Union, Soviet foreign policy, international politics, and Russian refugee life
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1977.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Access Points
Newsweek; Civil rights--Soviet Union; Dissenters--Soviet Union; Jews--Soviet Union; Russians in foreign countries; World politics; Soviet Union; Russia (Federation); Soviet Union--Foreign relations; Soviet Union--Politics and government--1936-1953; Soviet Union--Politics and government--1953-1985; Soviet Union--Social conditions; United States--Foreign relations; Journalists
Series Decription
- Diary, 1968, 1972-74. (Box Box No. 1)
  Diary and diary notes, arranged chronologically.
- Correspondence, 1948-1973. (Box Box No. 1)
  Correspondence arranged alphabetically by last name of correspondent.
- Speeches and Writings, 1948-1971. (Box Box No. 1-3)
  Drafts and printed copies of speeches and writings, arranged alphabetically by title.
- Subject File, 1948-1973. (Box Box No. 3-7)
  Correspondence, notes, memoranda, reports, clippings, printed matter, etc., arranged alphabetically by subject.
- Miscellany. (Box Box No. 7)
  Clippings, miscellaneous printed matter, notes, etc.
Container list
- Diaries, 1968, 1972-74 (Box Box No. 1)
  - February 1968 (Box 1)
  - December 1972 - January 1974
- Correspondence, 1948-1973
  - A.B.C. Press Service (Amsterdam), 1948 (Box 1)
  - American Committee for the Liberation of the Peoples of Russia, Inc., 1952
  - Berg, H. T., 1953
  - Berlingske Tidende (Copenhagen), 1948
  - Blackstock, Paul W., 1963-64
  - Chekhov Publishing House (New York), 1951
  - East European Fund, Inc. (New York), 1951
  - Free Russia Fund, Inc. (New York), 1951
  - Garthoff, Raymond L., 1951
  - Hatch, Richard W., 1952
  - Herald Tribune (New York), 1951
  - Hovell, B. B., 1952
  - Kamkin, Victor (bookstore), 1963
  - Kelly, Edna F., 1952
  - Klay, Andor, 1973
  - Kline, Harry Byrd, 1973
  - Korbel, J. J., 1953
  - Leigh, W. Colston, Inc. (New York), 1963-66
  - Massachusetts Institute of Technology, 1952
  - Milanytch, Athanas M., 1953
  - Mylk, Eugene A., 1953
  - Ory, Joseph S., 1953
  - Picozzi, Mary, 1953
  - The Rand Corporation, 1951
  - Scribner's Publishing Company (New York), 1971
  - Sperber, Richard, 1953
  - Stanley, John, 1951
  - Trabue, William, 1951-52
  - Traylor, Idris R., Jr., 1968
  - U. S. Department of Justice. Office of the Attorney General., 1953
  - U.S. Department of State. Division of Research for USSR and Eastern Europe., 1952
  - Miscellaneous
- Speeches and Writings, 1948-1971
  - Abraham Abramovich (Box 1)
  - An Attempt at an Autobiography, February 8, 1971
  - Clippings of published articles by L. Volkov, 1948-1959
  - Control of the Soviet Army
  - David and Tovarishch
  - Devushki - Smertnitsy (Women of Death). English translation included.
  - Georgi Malenkov
  - Klimentii Efremovich Voroshilov
  - Letter to the Russian People
  - Guerrilla Warfare
  - Interview with R. L. Garthoff, undated
  - The Long-Range Air Force of the Soviet Union (Box 2)
  - A Partisan Detachment in European USSR
  - The Pit of Death
  - Plan - Efektivnaia Psikhologicheskaia Voina Protiv Sovetskoi Armii v Mirnoe Vremia i vo Vremia Voiny (A Plan - Effective Psychological Warfare Against the Soviet Army in Peacetime and During War)
  - Printsipial'nye Razgovory - Tsikl Radio Peredach Dlia Sovetskikh Ofitserov (Principal Conversations - A Cycle of Radio Broadcasts for Soviet Officers)
  - Proposed projects
  - The Red Army and the Army of the U.S.A.
  - The Soviet Army and the West, October 1948
  - The Soviet Officer
  - Soviet Partisans
  - Soviet Society: Attitudes and Reactions (in Russian)
  - Soviet Society and Soviet Man Today
  - Spasenie Sbitogo Letchika (Rescue of a Shot Down Pilot)
  - Speaking engagements
  - Stena Placha (Wailing Wall)
  - Tainy Dvizhenii Kremlia (Secrets of Kremlin Operations) (Box 3)
  - Two Worlds
  - Vysshii Politicheskii Komandnyi Sostav Sovetskoi Armii (Higher Political Command Structure of the Soviet Army)
  - Ya Yevrey - I'm a Jew, March 23, 1971
  - Miscellaneous drafts and notes
- Subject File, 1948-1973
  - Agreements and contracts (Box 3)
  - Agreements between the government of the United States and Leon Volkov, 1951-52
  - American Political Science Association
  - Association of Former Servicemen of the Soviet Army
  - Association of Post-war Refugees from the Soviet Union
  - Boiter, Albert, Five Years of `Samizdat' - A Bibliography,April 1971
  - Brzezinski, Zbigniew
    - American Globalism (reprint, Survey, No. 58, January 1966)
    - Five Years After Khrushchev (reprint, Survey, No. 72, Summer 1969)
    - The Soviet Past and Future (reprint, Encounter, March 1970)
  - Clippings on Leon Volkov, 1953-54 (Box 4)
  - Columbia University. School of International Affairs. The Soviet Union and Arms Control: Report on a Study of Soviet Attitudes Toward Arms Control and Disarmament. Prepared for the United States Arms Control and Disarmament Agency, 1963-64
  - Danilov, Vladimir Stepanovich, Serious Talks - Cycle of Broadcasts to Soviet Officers
  - East-West transactions as reported in the press, June 1972 - August 1973
  - Expenditures, expenses, financial matters
  - Freedom Foundation 1950 Awards Presentation, New York
  - Goralik, Nikolai, a Soviet refugee's description of conditions in the Soviet Union just before World War II
  - Iurasov, S., Na Repetitsii `Letchikov' (At a Rehearsal of Pilots)
  - Klay, Andor C.
    - Curriculum vitae
    - Disputes
    - Doctrine
    - The Vanishing Crown
  - Koriakov, Mikhail, Partiinaia Liniia (Party Line)
  - Malakov, Sergei
    - The Fugitives, April 1954
    - Letchiki (The Fliers)
    - Lichnoe Schast'e (Personal Happiness)
    - Piesa v 3-kh Deistviiakh (A Play in 3 Acts) (Box 5)
    - Zhizn' Vtoraia (Second Life)
  - Moorer, Admiral Thomas H., United States Military Posture for FY 1974, a statement before the Senate Armed Services Committee, March 28, 1973
  - Newsweek magazine
  - Nieman Fellowship, Harvard University, 1963
  - The Night They Raided Minsky's, 1961-63
  - Novosti Press Agency (Moscow)
    - Dadyants, Georgi, Confidence in the Prospects of Development - President Pompidou Ends His Tour of the Soviet Union
    - Pekarsky, Leonid, The USSR: Rhythm of Economy
    - Soviet Jews: Facts and Fiction
  - Oral statement of Steven Lazarus, Deputy Assistant Secretary for East-West Trade, Department of Commerce, before the Joint Economic Committee of the United States, July 19, 1973
  - Peterson, Peter G., U.S. - Soviet Commercial Relationships in a New Era,August 1972
  - Pis'mo A. D. Sakharova, V. F. Turchina i R. A. Medvedeva Rukovoditeliam Partii i Pravitel'stva (A Letter from A. D. Sakharov, V. F. Turchin and R. A. Medvedv to the Leaders of the Party and the Government), March 19, 1970
  - Press excerpts dealing with international news events
    - June 15, 1964 - February 13, 1965
    - February 14, 1966 - October 8, 1966
    - October 10, 1966 - September 30, 1967 (Box 6)
    - October 2, 1967 - August 10, 1968
    - August 12, 1968 - June 14, 1969
    - November 1973
  - Programma Demokraticheskogo Dvizheniia Sovetskogo Soiuza (The Program of the Democratic Movement of the Soviet Union)
  - Radio Liberty panel discussion of western Samizdat experts, undated
  - The Radio Liberty Register of `Samizdat', February 1971 (Box 7)
  - Radio Reports, Inc., texts of Leon Volkov's articles, 1953
  - Sakharov, A. D. Razmyshleniia o Progresse, Mirnom Sosushchestvovanii i Intellektual'noi Svobode (Reflections on Progress, Peaceful Co-existence and Intellectual Freedom)
  - Shorin, Boris
    - The Life of a Soviet Jew
      - I. Child of the Revolution
      - II. The Beginning of the War
      - VII. The Red Army in Europe
  - The Soviet Review (White Plains, New York)
    - Vol. Xl, No. 2, Summer 1970
    - Vol. Xl, No. 1, Spring 1970
  - U.S. Department of Commerce. Bureau of the Census. Foreign Demographic Analysis Division.
    - Demographic Trends in the U.S.S.R.: 1950 to 1990, by Frederick A. Leedy, May 1971
    - Manpower Trends in the U.S.S.R.: 1950 to 1980, by Murray Frshback, May 1971
  - U.S. exports to the U.S.S.R. by major product groups, 1971-73
  - U.S. trade status and prospects with socialist countries, September 1973
  - Zasorin, V., Kollektivnost' v rabote (Collectivism in Action), (Partiinaia Zhizn', No. 3, February 1969)
- Miscellany
  - Miscellaneous notes, printed matter and other material (Box 7)